in our culture we believe that reality
means physical things
question is not whether the wool is real
or not the question is what is reality
in this Theory we are delighted to have
Professor Carr forston it's a
theoretical neuroscientist and an
authority on brain Imaging with Dr Chris
feel a philosopher and an independent
scientist into radical physics and
cognitive near our sides the topic of
our discussion today is
The Observer versus the observe welcome
Professor fiston welcome Dr Phil thank
you thank you so anything interesting
going for both of you have you been
anywhere lately beside work Professor
Christine no I'm afraid not I I'm just
yeah but my work is a holiday so
anything interesting going for you this
year oh
no I've had my uh stepmother visiting
for a week
so we've had a bit of a family week this
last week today
at your Chinese New Year yeah today this
year is a rabbit year
our calendar just changed today it's the
fifth day of it tell us briefly how your
career being my career
yeah yeah
um
so I started
as a medical trainee
um largely because I wanted to do what
was called in those days mathematical
psychology but my careers advisor
mistakenly thought that I had to be a
psychiatrist first so I went to
University
dutifully to study Psychiatry but was
able
um to do physics as an undergraduate so
I did Natural Sciences that included
psychology and physics and then became a
medic and a psychiatrist and then at the
earliest opportunity returned to
um the kind of research that I wanted to
do as an adolescent which was basically
mathematical psychology
so this book Professor Christine you
said you're going to write about
something about angel I heard a
talk about you talking about a book that
you want to write so if you're going to
write a book about an angel so
would it be your philosophy or would it
be something different
could you talk on that please yes
um yes the the idea the word or the
phrase or the
um the concept Angel was something
that arose uh during my early
psychiatric training from
um what was called in fact is called T
group therapy so part of my training was
to live in a Therapeutic Community
um with about 30 people with chronic
schizophrenia so I spent about two years
of my life living in this somewhat
isolated Community with psychiatric
nurses and doctors and people with
schizophrenia and with every
um week we would have several group
sessions and in these sessions all sorts
of wonderful things were talked about
and one of the more memorable themes was
this notion from a very high functioning
and very endearing
um uh young man with schizophrenia who
just came up with this notion of Angel
and just struck me as such an
interesting conjunction of things that
we don't normally associate you know a
nice expression of what's called night's
move or lateral thinking and in the
Psychopathology of schizophrenia but
also reflecting the creativity
um of somebody who's able to think
outside normal bounds and to transcend
the normal syntax and semantics in the
language that we usually share but I've
always remembered that instance
um and the phrase aim and I
thought to myself when I get older I
will write a book or the Angels but as I
get older I realize there is no time to
write books so I'm afraid I won't be
writing a book called Angel it
would be
thank you
Chris
you begin as an experimental physicist
could you tell us more
uh well I beginning graduate school
working at a small accelerator
doing nuclear structure physics
and uh
partway through that era
I by for various reasons switched into
philosophy
and took up with people doing artificial
intelligence
and uh
shortly after that ended up applying
some of that work in work for the Human
Genome Project so I spent a good deal of
my career in the human Human Genome
Project
so I have kind of a mixed bag from past
so it used to find time to be a
volunteer as a firefighter right Chris
a small village in New Mexico
and the fire department was one of the
things that held our
small village with a very diverse
population together
and so I spent a few years doing that oh
it was very interesting
um
dealt with a lot of car wrecks on icy
roads in the middle of the winter
thank you so two great minds let's get
serious now so when we say reality in
our culture we say reality is mean
physical thing
so
shall we go to to call first what did
you mean when we say reality I'm trying
to
um when you say what do we mean I would
imagine that um from a philosophical
point of view we're talking about
metaphysics so yesterday I was given a
briefing tutorial on metaphysics
um and from the point of view of
um
the free energy principle which is the
lens through which I usually use uh you
view many things and reality I guess
would correspond to
um the states or the configuration of
things beyond our sensorium beyond our
Markov blanket beyond our holographic
screen and so they would be the putative
causes of the things that we can read
from nature or that we
um would think about in terms of the
sensory Impressions and our sensory
epithelia or as I'm hoping Chris will
talk about
um the the sensory bits the readable
bits on some screen or Veil or boundary
or holographic um screen that separates
me from the rest of the universe
so reality on that vehicle is just the X
the exterior
um
and strictly speaking from my point of
view uh that that reality is something
which is constructed on the inside
um and uh can only kind of insight as
being our awareness our experience
yeah constructed inside yeah yeah so so
the the I I imagine that um you will
want to talk about
um this issue from the perspective of
the free energy principle read in two
ways read from the point of view of a
classical
um
physicists point of view and possibly
also nowadays A cognitive neuroscientist
point of view uh in the sense of things
like predictive processing but there's
another way of reading it which may be a
more generic way which is the Quantum
information theoretic way of
understanding things uh that I'm hoping
to learn
um more about by when you start quizzing
Chris
um so the classical uh the classical
view
um means that you are separating all
states of Any Given Universe into
um separate subsets with a particular
partition that separates or individuates
the internal States the interior of
something from the exterior the external
States and there are that separation is
um defined in terms of a Markov blanket
a blanket blanket outside
so if my if I am um somewhere in my
brain or my brain is is part of me then
the internal States would be my neuronal
States and my scent the sensory part of
my Markov blanket would be those signals
that correspond to sensory receptors say
you know vision and hearing but also
interception anything
um that
um reports or
um signifies changes in the outside in
the external states that that is
available to me so when I talk about the
inside I I mean the internal the bulk on
the inside of say a brain the kind of
thing that we study with brain Imaging
for example or indeed make inferences
about it as experimental psychologists
using uh psychophysics
um or other psychological tools to make
a guess about what's going on on the
inside of somebody's head
thank you Chris
uh well I certainly won't disagree with
that uh I'll translate your question a
bit to uh what are we talking about when
we talk about the physical
and here we can
look back at the history of physics as a
discipline
uh which evolved from something that
talked about
uh ordinary objects like planets and
cannonballs and
such
into something that now uh
is formulated
at least in many sectors of the
discipline isn't it as an information
theory that basically talks about
information and information processing
so in a sense the boundaries between
physics and Computing are starting to
dissolve in at least certain parts of
physics
Quantum cosmology for example
so when we talk about the physical
uh we're talking about something that
can be characterized in terms of some
sort of State space of something that
has distinguishable
configurations or States
and
so when we talk about the physical in a
sense we're we're making some assumption
about how we're going to characterize
what can be distinguished
and hence we're talking about
information which is uh how
what it means to distinguish something
is to talk about information
so I tend to think about your question
uh and and also Carl's answer
in terms of a division of some universe
as Carl was saying
uh and some physicists refer to this as
a Multiverse
uh into two pieces
of
that exchange information by interacting
by physically interacting
and to ask what does that exchange of
information look like how can we model
that exchange of information and
how can we model
what the systems on both sides of this
this division that we've stipulated
how can we model what they do with the
information
so how does each agent or entity act on
the other one
and a natural way to think about what
they do with the information is is
clearly the theory of computation uh
they're processing the information in
some way
so it's very natural to think of this
this physical interaction as we would
call it as a communication between two
entities who are each receiving
information from the other
doing something with it uh which we can
think of as a decision process or a
computational process
and then they're sending a message back
or they're acting on the other system in
some in some physical way all these ways
of of talking are formally completely
equivalent
so one can bring the language of
communication in the language of
computing to bear on on any physical
interaction
so uh
this naturally raises the question if we
think of of each system as some kind of
information processor
how do they structure the input that
they receive from the other system
and uh one way to to think about that
question is to ask uh can they detect
a correlated patterns
in the input that they get from the
other system
so if we think of this in communication
language
can they detect words or sentences or
other meaningful uh subsets
in the communications they get from the
other system
if we think about it in terms of a sense
like vision
uh we would ask can they see objects
that hold together over time
and
being able to detect such structure in
the information that they receive that
each receives from the other system is
necessary in order to do any sort of
prediction
so when Carl talks about the fep
it's a least action principle that has
to do with minimizing uncertainty about
what one's interaction partner will do
next
and uh
being able to do predictions requires
being able to to capture some kinds of
uh regularity is in the in the in the
input coming from the other system so it
has to be able to locate parts of that
signal that have relatively low entropy
in other words some sort of relative
stability over time
so if we pursue this line of thinking
of were very quickly led to viewing what
we call ordinary objects like uh
planets or billiard balls or computers
or each other
as constructs as Carl put it
because they are
as of low entropy in the signals that
we're receiving from whatever it is that
we're interacting with
that we see uh only via the messages
that it sends to us or only via the
actions that it takes on us
uh and
so uh what is often called reality
uh what what we see all around us and
hear all around us
is is in that sense a construct it's
something that we have to be smart
enough to put together
using whatever information processing
facilities that we have uh including of
course those in our brains
and that that leads us of course almost
immediately to ask a different question
which is
lots of the things we see around us uh
look for all the world like other agents
rather like us
uh not just other humans but all other
organisms and so we can ask how did they
see their world yeah what what is an
object for them
uh how do they view uh what their
environment is doing to them all the
time
and
so one is quickly drawn into a kind of
ethology if you will
uh concerned with how other organisms
process what they're getting from their
environments thank you Carl do you have
anything else before we move on lots of
things come to mind I I think it might
be quite useful
um just to paraphrase some of the terms
that Chris was using
um in the language of inference and
Bayesian inference in particular and
just to put a bit of intuition for those
people who are not as
um fluent in Quantum information
theories as as other people are yeah so
you know words like computation
information processing uh I would also
say measurement
um
and be written as Chris nicely expressed
you know what natural way do we have of
describing the the sense that is made of
this information that is arriving
um on our sensory epithelia or on our um
a Markov blanket or
um in the um the quantum formulation on
the holographic screen
um one way of talking about information
processing is just to cast it as belief
updating where you've introduced now the
notion of a probability distribution so
if you just think about reality being a
particular dynamics of probability
distributions very much like quantum
physics
um then
um what you are talking about when you
talk about information processing is the
change in some probabilistic
representation on the inside in the
brain for example that is induced or
consequent Upon A Certain set of then
three inputs and this belief updating
can be read in many different ways you
know that you from a purely mathematical
in terms of movement on a statistical
manifest filter every point in these
special spaces these special manifolds
corresponds to a certain belief where a
belief is just a probability
distribution over reality which are the
external States so you never see them
but you can make inferences about them
so for me information processing is just
a movement on a statistical manifold and
then Chris also mentioned the word
structure you know how do we make sense
of how do we detect those regimes of low
entropy those
um
bits of information that have some
causal structure so in things like
radical constructivism and indeed uh
Bayesian
modeling this would be structure
learning it's getting the frames of
reference right so that you are using
the right kind of manifold to do your
information processing by moving around
on that manifold so that you can make
sense of the data looking for symmetries
and invariances
um that would correspond to again as
Chris noted objects have certain
invariances you know that they have
certain features that are invariant to
their location and their location may be
your location as a construct doesn't
necessarily depend upon the object that
that is at that location so keysing
apart finding the conditional
independencies is one way of looking at
getting these frames of reference fit
for purpose to do the kind of
information for us to say and the best
kind is the one that makes this makes
sense of all these sensory signals
um sometimes you can you well some
people refer to that as sort of being
Bayes optimal being optimal in the sense
of finding that structure that frame of
reference on the inside that upon which
this belief amputating and information
processing plays out that renders all of
those input as likely as possible and
that's you know it is from my point of
view it's as simple as that um so you
can score this as likely as possible in
terms of things like Bayesian model
evidence or
um the complement or the inverse of that
things like um variational free energy
or prediction error surprise or
information Theory or more in terms of
psychologist's surprise so the best
stuff is the stuff which are the best
sense making is a sense making that
renders you the least surprised about
seeing this pattern of sensory
Impressions from reality out there
you'll never know what reality out there
is doing but uh at least you can make
the best guess of this by finding the
right kinds of structures what Chris has
done though he's taken us right into uh
the much more glorious realm of two
sense making systems that are talking to
each other and further to that the
there's some isomorphism there so you
imagine that's two
um
highly
sophisticated and evolved structures
that are passing messages across their
with a shared screen if you like or a
shared Markov bag that's a shared
separation
um and you know all the interesting
issues that arise from that that can be
cast in terms of
um say generalized synchrony from the
point of view of classical dynamical
systems theory from the point of view
entanglement in in Quantum
um
three months but the other interesting
um perspective that uh Chris has uh has
his new month of the argument is that to
get this minimum surprising maximally
predictable
um State of Affairs then there has to be
a shared narrative on both sides a
shared structure to establish this
synchrony which could be read in terms
of sense making and information
processing as basically resolving the
hermeneutics problem
um and of course how do we do that well
it's with language so uh like you know
and if you generalize that notion of
language then all communication is just
good belief updating in the service of
expanding something out there that
actually shares some reference frame or
some to share some narrative or World
model or the statistical manifold with
me and I have to learn uh I have to
learn about you they have to speak the
same language and we converge upon the
same kind of structure just to make sure
that the sensations that we receive are
as likely and as predictable as possible
thank you so last week we have Don and
Levin on our show so don't reduce
reality to a network of conscious agents
then
he then went one step further that was
he reduced all this multiplicity and
diversity of Pontius aging into a single
consciousness
because they're all they're all our
conscious experiences
so the Consciousness is the common
factors of it so
my question is at what level one can be
described as having a conscious
experience though
can we go to Chris
I take a fairly
um
radical or
deflationary or one could call it
various things view of this
oh yeah
and uh
reason in this way that what we call
experience
is always uh determinate or classical
uh it's it's what it's what in a sense
we mean by classical information
uh you know we we don't see
Schrodinger's cat as being dead and
alive we see Schrodinger's cat as being
either one or the other and
uh we don't see people as being located
both here and there we see them located
in one place and saying one thing and so
on so that's that's classical
information
and from a
fairly strict kind of
Quantum information theoretic
perspective
the only place that one expects to see
classical information
is on a boundary between two interacting
systems
so
if we think of classical information as
only encoded on boundaries
and if we think of experience
uh as classical information
then it's fairly natural to think that
experience is what's happening on a
boundary
and because that's where the classical
information is it's not anywhere else
in this very kind of strict Quantum
theoretic point of view
so
in that case one can think of the
universe
if you will is this big
system
of which we can describe using at least
a quantum formalism
and one can think of slicing it in
various ways
and so slice it in some arbitrary way
you've created a boundary
now that boundary may not be stable if
the if the interaction across that
boundary is very strong
then the boundaries not going to
pick out two systems that one can talk
about as if they're different
oh and formally if if the interaction is
strong enough that the entanglement
entropy across that boundary is large
uh then those systems don't really have
separate identities they're too
correlated
to be considered to be just in
exchanging classical information but if
the interaction across the boundary that
you've picked is fairly weak
uh then the two systems are more or less
independent of each other and you can
think of them as separate entities that
have their own States
and that are exchanging some relatively
small amount of information with each
other compared to the amount of
information that they've got inside
and that's that's
the place where the free energy
principle is helpful because it depends
on this
conditional independence of one system
from another
so now if if you've if you've picked a
slice like that when you
you slice the universe up
then that boundary is going to encode
some classical information
and I see no reason not to think of
all of that
classical information is experiential or
think of it in experiential terms
and we're very familiar with that in our
own case
and we're
reasonably familiar with it in the case
of animals like us
and we have essentially no familiar with
familiarity at all with it in the case
of other systems but
um
I don't see any reason not to think of
it that way for arbitrary systems
that interact sufficiently weekly with
their environments
so I would be uh either bold or crazy
and just say we should think of
experience in general as the classical
information that's encoded on boundaries
where the boundaries can be arbitrary
but the amount of classical information
they encode depends on
uh whether they separate systems that
are uh separable or Mutual mutually
conditionally and dependent and the way
that Carl was mentioned I agree with
that absolutely entirely
um one nice thing about
um the quantum formulation of the fep is
its scale-free nature and
um one could read what Chris just said
as
um saying that there are Markov blankets
and many many different scales and um
certain kinds of
um
systems that are enshrouded in a
particular
blanket or boundary
um will certainly have it's only be
described as doing belief updating and
um making sense of data experiencing the
sensory inputs in in the um in the
formulation of the Chris just offered
um
and as such I think it's perfectly
permissible to say that there can be
um a universe of collective
consciousnesses
um just in virtue of the fact that you
know as we've just heard there are many
many ways of carving up conditional
independencies and developing Markov
blankets at different scale so I see no
mathematical problem
um with having distributed cognition and
you're a mathematical form of collective
Consciousness in which there is a
minimization of the joint free energy of
multiple Markov blankets that are
already founded by a Markov blanket
defying that particular community of
sense making agents for example
those sanctions could be people but I
would also so maybe just think about
um the brain as a very carefully
structured
um Ensemble of Markov blanketed bounded
um systems neural populations
specialized cortical areas that
themselves comprise uh lots of
delicately structured Markov blankets at
the level of single neurons and then
within a single neuron axonal dendritic
processes a ride down to to the
molecular level so viewed it from the
scale free perspective from Gaia down to
down to
um the you know the molecular scale
um then if the same kinds of principles
apply and there's I suppose can be read
in terms of sense making and sentience
of a basal
um sort of elementary form then it can
be no other way that that Consciousness
cannot be tied to one privilege knock
off blanket so I think that that's an
interesting observation
um and um
it it does strike me though that you may
be asking
um there may be a difference between
experience and qualitative experience so
you may be asking about qualia uh and
you know does every yeah yeah
um does every
um individuated uh boundary system
um are you licensed to suppose that it
has the capacity to experience
qualitatively in you know in a
phenological sense
um I think that's you know so we're
touching on things like pan psychism now
um and I think there are two ways that
you can you can read this the first is
yes obviously
um there is a basal sense making a basal
distributed cognition a distributed
Consciousness you know that is evident
in the in any kind of communicating
sparsity Capital system from you know
multiple molecules to multiple cells to
organs in my body to to institutions
or you know bodies of people
um or you could argue well yes that's
fine but are there any special kinds of
sense making that um would give you the
um the qualitative experience that
people talk about in philosophy I would
suggest that that that there may be
um and you know
um after many years of conversing with
uh people in the field I think one key
distinction
between the kind of experience that is
generic to any
self-evidising uh system that can be
individuated from its milia it's
external miliarics echinitial
environment is the capacity to select to
act on the world out there
in such a way that it has consequences
for other sensory impressions
so if I was limiting myself to the brain
for example and I was thinking like a
psychologist this would be attention
mental action actively selecting what
kinds of sensory Impressions make a
difference to my information processing
and my belief updating
um if
um I was a motor physiologist I'd be
talking about being able to move say my
eyes and look at that so seeing becomes
looking at
um if I was a physiologist I would make
a distinction between the things that I
have causative
experience of and things that I don't so
I when I breathe I can attend to and
also using my muscles
exert volitional control of my
respiration but I can't do that with my
heart so I'm not aware I don't have a
phonology of my my cardiac cycle that I
do of my respiratory title so I think
that the the special kinds of actions
the acting the the other way if you like
the other direction of travel through
the boundaries or in the other direction
of travel in terms of information
[Music]
um channels that transcend or transgress
these boundaries or or the Markov
blanket which is writing to the boundary
or then acting upon the other side which
could be another person I think that may
be an important kind of
um
structure that that would be
um possibly
um necessary to actually have a
qualitative experience as opposed to
just an experience
thank you so Chris it's it's an
entanglement then between the two right
through the user interface like Don
saying
so it's an entangle system between the
two interactions then right is that what
you're saying
uh well entanglement is one of those
words that has different meanings uh in
different disciplines
in in physics
entanglement or quantum entanglement
is uh
defined as the state of
non-non-separability
so if a system is entangled
then one can't talk about the states of
its components independently
so uh
entanglement is in in that sense is a
limiting case
in which the interaction across the
boundary is
both
strong enough
and
um
correlated enough
that one can no longer distinguish
between the two interacting systems
so that's a that's a very different
meaning
than some more classical uses of the
term entanglement
which just mean a very close correlation
so entanglement is the word is used in
physics of
means a correlation that effectively
destroys separate identities
[Music]
so if if a system is entangled
uh one in a sense can't draw a
meaningful boundary across it
um but I I would like to say something
uh in response to what Carl just said
and in your question about you know
since real real Consciousness
uh experience right real phenomenal
consciousness
it clearly depends on
um I mean organisms or systems in
general can clearly vary enormously in
what they can detect about the world
and how they can act on the world
for example you could ask for a system
uh
can it detect spatial dimensionality in
the world
you know does it live in a world that
that appears to it to have any spatial
coordinates
and clearly for our kind of
Consciousness we have to be able to to
Overlay some spatial coordinate system
on our experience or it doesn't make any
sense at all we can't talk about object
identity we can't talk about motion
uh we can't talk about any of that stuff
without spatial coordinates
and we can ask can a system detect the
passage of time
which requires having a certain kind of
memory
so that I can tell now from what
happened you know a few seconds ago
that depends on my being able to
remember a few seconds ago
so these are capabilities that systems
have to have to have experiences like
ours
but I think of a dividing line that I
might like to propose is
between systems that are capable of
acting in order to get more information
in the future
which which Carl has characterized in
his work as acting in pursuit of
epistemic value
uh in an ordinary language when one
would characterize this curiosity acting
with curiosity
and I think that uh
what is characteristic of the systems
that we
tend to regard as having
phenomenal consciousness of the sort
that we have is that they act with
curiosity fairly clearly
other mammals for example are all
curious
so I would just throw that into the
conversation as a as a
a thing that I think characterizes the
sorts of systems that we regard as
interesting
from the point of view of what their
experience is like
you know and just to um bring the last
two points together
in
acting in a way to resolve your expected
surprise which is just uncertainty that
would be the definition of curiosity you
have to have
um a frame of reference a structure on
the inside that can predict the
consequences of any particular action
um so by definition this introduces a
form of temporality you know whether the
agent knows that this is time uh but
there's certainly an ordinal aspect that
something will happen contingent upon
doing this and I think that This lends a
um well some people refer to the
temporal thickness or temporal depth to
the way that we make sense of data and I
think that that comes for free
um when you talk about systems that have
this uh this kind of curiosity curious
creatures
um that I think you you would have to
entertain in order to uh to um as
um requisite for having any kind of
phenomenal Consciousness the reason I
say that of course is that that
um modeling the consequences of action
over some time like
um and sequence just as memory so you
know I think the two come for free from
the same commitment to certain systems
that have this capacity to not only
resolve or minimize their surprise in
the moment but also act upon a world in
a way that they anticipate that they
will minimize their expected surprise
and resolve uncertainty and it is
something that has underwritten
um
all of our behavior and certainly
behavior in statistics since since the
1950s so this was
um this is called the principle of
optimal ex Bayesian experimental design
namely what is the best experiment
what's the best action what's the best
sort of writing to the world acting upon
the world
um that will minimize my uncertainty and
that's the same as maximizing my
expected Information Gain that you can
compute so if you know the state of the
world do you know what you don't know
then you can estimate how much
uncertainty you can resolve if I did
that as opposed to this and of course
that's just what we do as scientists we
design our experiments exactly in the
way that resolve the greatest amount of
uncertainty about our competing
hypotheses as scored by maximizing
expected Information Gain it's something
that re-emerged in the 1990s in the guys
in machine learning is active learning
what data point do I commit to trying to
search for that's going to best resolve
the uncertainty about the unknowns in my
particular World moral or statistical
model of of these data so I think what
Christmas just said is absolutely uh
absolutely Central and notice that there
are probably very few of these kinds of
systems in our universe
um you know a thermostat doesn't have
memory a thermostat but very simply
cannot plan what we're talking about
here are systems that at least look as
if they are panning so there's a whole
universe of very functional very
adaptive
systems creatures particles phenotypes
out there that don't plan the weather
Evolution
um thermostats
um but there may be a small number of
things that do have this these temporary
thick World models under the hood the
structures that we were talking about
before that enable them to invince this
kind of curiosity and it was exactly
that kind of action I was I was sort of
hinting at before but I didn't think we
were going to get quite so foreign into
the weeds in terms of
that's exactly that's my brain how it
function yeah I'm sorry the don't fear
it because it's how my brain went
something stuck I need to get it out
so we quickly move on you know when when
Chris say observers is everywhere
observation is an information transfer
Chris say that
so if you have to Define what an
observer is could you define it
precisely what an observer through a
physics science
and Kyle could you define on the
Neuroscience site because to me Observer
is the Observer has information am I
correct it could be looking at like the
ego or the identity but Chris say
observers is everywhere so can we just
unpack The Observer that what both of
you men could Chris
sure uh when I talk about an observer I
admittedly use the term very Loosely in
a way that I think lots of of
physicists do when they see things say
things like The Observer is just another
quantum system
I I think of an observer as
minimally uh
any system
that interacts with an environment
of
such that the joint Observer environment
System state is separable so they're not
entangled
uh and under those conditions one can
talk about the state of the Observer and
how the state of the Observer changes as
it receives information from the
environment and as it acts on the
environment
so an observer is something that can
receive information and act
in a conditionally independent way from
its environment
now that's an extremely minimal
definition
and lots of things qualify so one can
now start layering abilities on top of
this
system
to make it more and more capable so when
we use the word observer in English
we're we're referring to systems that at
least can pick out different objects in
the environment and act on them
reasonably specifically and I say
reasonably specifically because there
are no actions without side effects
uh but can act reasonably specifically
on objects that it could distinguish
from the rest of what's going on in its
environment
so this gets back to our previous
conversation about temporal depths and
object identity and all of these other
things
so
there are these two senses of Observer
one of which is extremely minimal
and only really depends on the existence
of a Markov blanket which is what
separability gives you
and the other which can be arbitrarily
sophisticated uh with with
large a large memory for example a large
ability to model statistically uh the
data that it receives
and an ability to act with a fair degree
of precision on
the environment that it sees
and I would say everything in between as
an observer with some set of
capabilities or other
they may be fairly small and they may be
quite sophisticated Kyle
um yeah again I agree entirely um I mean
in my world observation which is the
thing that defines something as an
observer measurement inference and
existence are all the same thing
um so again from a different
inflationary
taking the deflationary perspective that
Chris has articulated and anything that
can be separated or identified
individuated from its embedding
environment must by definition have a
Markov blanket that Markov blanket must
comprise some sensory States so it must
be
um its existence
belies the fact that is evidence that it
is observing In This Very minimalist
um sense that it is processing sensory
information
and I would contend that you know this
can be read I repeat as measurement it
can be repeated you're in the sort of
quantum or physicists sense
um
and that very
um minimal definition of what it is to
be an observer it is to be an observer
is just to exist
from the point of even Neuroscience
you're a scientist
um I think you're talking about this
more elaborate kind of observation that
has this curiosity attached to it
um so the kinds of particles that I
spend my time measuring
um our people and brains
um so these these particles these very
complicated very expressive particles
um have a particular kind of observation
that basically we were talking about
before which in which is
um the kind of observation that they can
plan to make the good observations the
uncertainty resolving observations the
um the just is an expression of this
responding to epistemic affordances
responding to Salient cues in the um
um in third queues in the environment to
show this um curiosity that
characterized so if you limit
um sort of observation to this informed
and observation then I think then I
would then that that would be the kind
of Observer that uh that I would study
as
um as a neuroscientist is that like is
that a sufficient definition
um you know
I do repeat that the notion of an
observer
is
um
it's almost unnecessary
um in the sense that as soon as you can
separate anything from everything else
the coupling between everything else and
the thing in question
constitutes an effect a kind of
observation you know then the
interesting questions are what happens
on the inside of the thinking question
uh that's basically the story that the
fep Tells in terms of trying to describe
this information processing this belief
updating
in relation to things like Bayesian
inference and sense making and
minimizing minimizing prediction error
and ultimately planning to minimize
prediction error by taking the right
kinds of actions designing the right
experiments
which is exactly what we're doing now
yeah so you know you you asking me
questions and me and me trying to work
out what's going to resolve your
uncertainty uh this is exactly that's
kind of curious behavior that I think it
characterizes the kind of observers I
think that you're talking about when it
comes to getting a response from a
neuroscientist
yeah yes have you heard anything to add
on
no I think that that sums it up quite
nicely I I I really like the the the
motto uh to be an observer is just to
exist yes I completely agree so
much and David Bowen say The Observer is
the observed so what's your thought on
that then The Observers say
The Observer is the observed it's like
when we talk about the inside of it
right you have an observer position
you're having a new goal so you can
observe yourself that's what they're
talking about right
um so I just wonder what's your
thoughts on that
right because your Observer is just
existing whereas if we can go deeper
The Observer is just observing with no
content that's what I actually thought
it is so I'm still a bit confused on
that but yeah
yeah so I I think that's a great
question that could be taken in two
directions One Direction which I think
we won't go down is that there is a
simple truth that whenever there is an
observer there is also an observed in a
simple sense that we're talking about
before if you have any universe and you
carve it into two you put a partition or
a boundary between one part of the
universe and the other part of the
universe and then one becomes an
observer but there's also something on
the other side that is
um is observing The Observer and that
phrase observing The Observer is a good
description of me as a neuroscientist
spending most of my life trying to work
out what's going on inside other
people's ends and it's you know it's
actually a very
um
difficult problem
um but I think you're talking no now
more about me observing my information
processing in the spirit of things like
high order thought theories of
Consciousness or metacognition
um perhaps even touching upon the
Notions of self-modeling
um speaking here on the work of people
like Thomas metzinger and I think that
that
um that's an essential part of the kind
of observers that we're talking about
when we're talking about people uh and
possibly you know most animals that yeah
I think probably most animals
um and
um in a sense that that sort of um
observing The Observer uh The Observer
becoming the observed is a necessary
consequence of something that you
actually said in your question which is
the notion of debt so depth can
certainly be applied in the temporal
domain but also has an important um it
is an important attribute of the
structure that we use to do our
information processing and our belief
updating the structures I'm referring to
structure here in the spirit of
structure learning a world model or an
internal model of what caused my
Sensations now if you have a deep
structure then by definition you have a
hierarchical depth and if you have a
hierarchical depth each hierarchy is
observing what's going on at the level
below
and so the very existence of systems
that whose bulk or internal states are
doing the kind of information processing
that enable them to plan
of a hierarchical structure they have
both a temporal and hierarchical depth
and therefore they they must if you like
have this
attribute that you can read them as
observing themselves simply because they
possess this hierarchical structure just
to finish
um that notion of deep is exactly what
underlies deep learning in machine
learning so and when when you look at
the Fantastic achievements of sense
making and sort of recapitulating saying
generative artificial intelligence
genitive AI it invariably involves a
deep neural network or a deep World
model and that deepness just depends
upon having hidden layer upon hidden
layer upon hidden layer that defines
this hierarchical structure that's sort
of
um frames of reference and frames of
reference of frames of reference usually
increasing in time as you get deeper and
deeper into the hierarchy or in some
instances a heterarchy so I think
there's there is literally a deep truth
to the notion that the kind of sense
making and the kind of
um the way that you and I experience our
world
um is
um deep in the sense that it can be read
as a hierarchical sense making where
each um each level is both observed and
observer it is observing the level below
and it is observed by the level by the
level above thank you Chris
well I I think that's uh
excuse me a very nice way of putting it
um
I I would refer to some terminology that
uh
our our colleague Mike Levin has
proposed
of a what he calls a multi-scale
competency architecture which all
organisms have
each each level of the hierarchy is
competent to do certain things
essentially on its own without being
told
and it's that sense of hierarchy
where at each level there are certain
defined capabilities
that is at play here in these kinds of
hierarchical models
um but but I'd also go back to another
way of addressing your question in terms
of self-observation
and and ask what's the minimal kind of
self observation that's called for in
this kind of theory
and in a sense it's it's some kind of
observation of what is my stress level
you know what what is my current level
of uncertainty
um and one can see this as far down in
phylogeny as one chooses to look
so for example
of
molecular biologists very early studied
one of the earliest studied
systems in
microbes like E coli is the stress
response system
and it was first identified by studying
responses to heat stress so the whole
family of
response genes got called heat shock
genes
but they're really stress detectors
and
any any cell even down to to prokaryotic
or microbial cells
uh has a a huge repertoire of of stress
detectors and defensive strategies of
one kind or other
that don't make any sense
physiologically
unless we understand them as measuring
their own state
as being able to detect
that they're being attacked by viruses
or uh their temperature is high enough
that their proteins are starting to fall
apart and quit working
or they're too cold the opposite extreme
and and diffusion is no longer working
and so reactions are slowing down
so this sense of
self-observation if you will is is very
very deep biologically
and seems to be a
a defining feature of the things that we
refer to as alive it's just the
awareness of it right Chris
uh well yeah I don't think that the term
observe makes any sense without thinking
of being aware of what's one of one is
observant yeah
so yeah I think I think that the the
poor bacteria actually don't like it
when you heat them up too much
yes
[Music]
um just thinking
um
about that question from the point of
view or that point about uh stress
detectors
um on the point of view of Psychiatry
um and the sort of The Human Experience
I think there's
um another important uh truism here
um that
we've referred to or Chris has referred
to repeatedly The Importance of Being
precise the importance of rendering
everything predictable and unambiguous
as possible you know come in one way of
reading this
um
imperative that underlies curiosity is
to resolve uncertainty and keeping
things very very precise if if that's
the game and um
I would suggest it is the game in this
in in a you know in a very mathematical
sense that you know if I'm in the game
of minimizing the surprise I expect
following this action then I am simply
trying to minimize the expected
surprisal which is the entropy or the
uncertainty I'm always trying to resolve
uncertainty about my lived world
if I was able to measure the uncertainty
of my current state of being
then you can see the increases in
uncertainty uh are going to be have a
very negative valence and decreases of
uncertainty the kinds of things that I'm
going to Aspire to and in one sense of
course novelty seeking information
seeking is exactly to reduce that um
that that uncertainty but the converse
um I think holds the key to many
mechanical
um
understandings of Psychopathology and
anxiety so usually in Psychiatry when
you look at the
the sorts of aberrant belief updating
and sense making that underlie all sorts
of uh
um conditions
um ranging from a professional
compulsive disorder through to autism
schizophrenia through to
um depression
um then you can always find uh and not
least of course anxiety anxiety
disorders particularly generalized
anxiety disorders and and sort of
chronic stress all there's one common
theme throughout and that's a failure to
resolve uncertainty
um a failure to
eliminate in the right way the
uncertainty that you sense yourself as
currently experiencing there are all
sorts of ways of resolving uncertainty
you could just hide from the world so
you could have agrophobia or you could
become socially and emotionally
withdrawn
um and even physically you know manifest
psychometric symptoms of and severe
depression
um if you had severe autism uh one way
of minimizing your uncertainty and
surprises is to avoid any potential
situation in which was so interpersonal
interactions in which there's going to
be unpredictable or surprising responses
or indeed create your own predictable
Sensations just your skimming Behavior
self-stimulation behavior and I think
all of these
um sort of pathological although
strictly speaking there is no
pathological Behavior it's all baze
Optimum at some point um but these
aberrant kinds of behaviors you know if
the person was like me
um can always be read as an attempt to
minimize that the kind of stress that
this is stress which can be read
literally in terms of the entropy of the
uncertainty associated with particular
belief States during during your sense
making so I think that that perspective
uh has a lot of tactical utility when it
comes to formalizing theories of bad
sense making uh in Psychopathology and
indeed as you know has found a certain
Traction in feels like computational
Psychiatry thank you we're going to go
straight to Andy your question Andy who
your question choose oh okay wow um
thank you so much guys this is amazing
um my pre-prepared question I think has
just dissolved
um so so I'm think of this more just a
participation of the conversation in you
guys Minds is and this is for either of
you is an understanding of our
Consciousness
um dependent on some notion of
Consciousness being a fundamental thing
um separate from our sort of
physicalists understanding of the
universe you know like of you know
complex energetic information processes
arising from the standard model and plus
whatever sensible near future extensions
to that model might happen like like
necessarily fail in describing our
Consciousness um that's as good as I
think thank you so much Carl do you want
to take that first
yeah I think that that question speaks
to yeah what was quite a large part of
the focus of our conversation which I
think is the distinction between
um the Consciousness that has a
phenomenal aspect uh and usually how the
self-referential and perspective
perspectival aspect to it that can be
articulated not least to ourselves it
include some kind of self-modeling so I
would I would just fall back on
um this you know
the way that we would describe
the kinds of systems that can support
that kind of information processing and
modeling and I repeat sort of modeling
um oneself as part of the active process
of gathering the data that you are
trying to trying to model so again we
come back to this notion of soliciting
the right kind of information the right
kind of cues and feedback from the world
from nature from our from our partners
and our and our friends and colleagues
um uh which is this sort of curiosity
you're planning to resolve uncertainty
and I I repeat you know that is the
special Preserve of a very small number
of systems possibly just the handful of
people we've found we find on
um or animals that we find on on this
Earth and in that sense
um a description of
um measurement and
um the physics of measurement a
metrological approach to physics would
not be sufficient I think to fully
understand that kind of
Rich thick deep curious Consciousness
that has this phenomenal
um phonological attributes
um and I'll just
um I also just put out there for Chris's
comment
um you could argue that standard the
standard model and that physics and all
the mathematical and
um
narrative languages upon which that is
predicated is just a shared construct
it's just part of our world model our
sense making that actually inherits from
a kind of collective unconscious that
would be ascribed to
um evolutionary psychology or cultural
Niche construction but at the end of the
day it's just another hypothesis maths
is just another hypothesis that we use
to make sense it feels really solid
because it's shared so universally and
has that unreasonable decision and
efficacy just to come back to a really
key
um point that Chris has made repeatedly
if it if it's precise in its explanatory
power
then it's going to find a home in our
existential architectures the structures
of the way that we make sense or
anything that survives but in particular
the way that we make sense of our world
Chris over to you for that one yeah yeah
thank you all right
I I would just add that uh you know the
the standard model is a lovely construct
uh it's a theory of interactions and the
symmetries of interactions it's it's not
a theory of what exists
and uh essentially what we've been
talking about today
is a way of Shifting our thinking about
uh what systems are what it means to be
a system
that's interacting with an environment
and when one talks about
information exchange or information
or experience of ones using a language
that is not
captured strictly speaking by
uh a standard model like description of
the symmetries of interaction because
one's added to that description of
interaction
some description of the things that are
interacting
and that's uh
in in a sense has been provided by
physics with the notion of a particle or
the notion of a field but even
underlying those Notions uh is this very
informal notion of a system
and it's that notion of of a system
that I think has to be added
in order to uh
fully capture what we've been trying to
talk about today
I would say that that
what we've been discussing today is
mainly a different point of view on
the physics of interaction than
has typically been pursued in physics up
until I would say the past couple of
decades where a lot of attention has
gone to describing physical interactions
in terms of communication protocols and
information exchange using some of the
language that we've been using today
so I I don't think that one has to
assume if you will new metaphysics I
think when
uh just to take just has to take a
slightly different point of view on
things
sorry we're breaking in Andy can we move
on quickly to Kyle please wonderful and
um yeah I invited people to the stage
just to tweak the algorithm and bring um
more years
um to the um outstanding amazing
speakers here and thank you both very
much for being here
um a couple of things that I was
listening to that I took uh particularly
interest in first was like the
anticipation and the modeling I guess
I've uh been in sports activities and
careers in which uh I've had to have a
great deal of anticipation
um so much so that I I'm almost thinking
about the other
um aspect of it because uh when there is
no surprise people become kind of
conform they conform to the uh
conceptual understanding of um of the
system itself and they lose uh
spontaneity so I was just thinking about
the benefit of uh you stress because
address was mentioned before but there
is a distress in eustress and
spontaneity for surprise another quick
um and so I was just wondering if you
could just briefly touch upon uh
spontaneity Carl and then for the both
of you I was just wondering
um I've been hearing some stuff about
like collecting data for a
representation of self and I think this
is what marketers do in companies that
are taking all of our data they're kind
of like creating a digital twin to
anticipate how we will actively infer
throughout our lives and taking
advantage of that I was wondering if you
have anything to say about that
thank you I'll take the spontaneity
question which is a really interesting
question
um and I one could read that in one of
two ways so um in terms of uh say sports
physiology or um sort of the the odd the
agenda of uh becoming a good sports
person
um spontaneity may be read in terms of
automatization and habitatization
becoming fluent you know getting into
the flow in the particular situation in
which you have become skilled and and I
think that would just be an expression
of this imperative to
um do actively very precise belief
updating uh with um resolution of all
reducible uncertainties in exactly what
you're going to do
um and effectively you are responding
reflexively and automatically in the
situation
um through a series of movements or
responses over which you have Exquisite
control and also that you can predict
um expertly so this would be if you like
the end point of an uncertainty reducing
um scheme but there's another kind of uh
if you like spontaneity that is afforded
um when we now turn to the construction
of deeper and deeper models so you know
when one tries to model this kind of
process one then thinks okay well what
if we now put a deeper model or a deeper
layer on top of the lower layer that's
doing the spontaneous automated behavior
and
usually that there has a more
temporarily extended aspect to it
um and um and now contextualize
um uh and make sense of
um different the evolving of say a game
at a a uh at a much longer time scale
um what can happen with some uh you know
once was established these um deep
generative models or World models of me
performing in a particular context is
actually about apology where you start
to go back and start to attend to your
more fluent ultimate uh automatized
behaviors and that can completely
destroy the behavior and so I have
colleagues who spend a lot of their time
in clinics
um neurologists uh dealing with
functional medical
symptoms that arise when a sports
professional can no longer play tennis
or putt simply because they're focusing
they're attending to the things that had
previously been
learned over learned and and become
reflexive so this is one of those nice
instances of getting the estimates of
uncertainty and precision wrong in your
belief updating when you're actively
engaged with the world the final kind of
spontaneity I I guess you're hinting at
is really that that underwrites
creativity and the way that we can
spontaneously explore hypothesis spaces
um that provide alternative explanations
for our sensed world or indeed the world
that we can create in terms of
um being artists or poets or uh
inventive in our personal relationships
so that that that that
um I think that's a very different kind
of spontaneity and I think it speaks to
this impa this aspect of curiosity
there's imperative to resolve
uncertainty but if you want to resolve
uncertainty you have to have the
capacity to develop a state of
alternative hypothesis hypotheses over
which you can then resolve uncertainty
so um I would look at this uh as a one
fundamental aspect of novelty seeking
having spontaneous ideas aha moments
that just
um Encompass different explanations
officials for the way the world works
and then you once you have this
hypothesis space then you're able to
either create or secure evidence oh it
works like that this is a you know a
nice simple and Central resolving
explanation
well I'll I'll just make a remark that
uh when you talk about use stress
uh in a sense in a sense you're talking
about play
which is again something we observe in
in all of the organisms that we think of
as as having interesting sorts of
consciousness
so yeah I I agree that it goes back to
curiosity
but yeah thank you those are organisms
that can have fun
thank you
thank you Carla for that great questions
can we move to prakash quickly
yes thank you Ivy and um you know thank
you very much both the speakers very
deep dive into what we think of as
interaction between uh Observer and The
observed or what we call as
Consciousness in the material around it
I want to overstep the boundary a little
bit and go deeper and ask
if you're having a kind of spiritual
experience or if you are under the
influence of psychedelics
what what is the state of the Observer
there is the is there a witnessing that
happens without an observer and
I just want to explore a little bit on
that side because it is an altered state
of consciousness so I just want to see
what opinions you have on that
thank you
uh sure I'll say a little bit about that
I think one characteristic of these
sorts of experiences
is an absence of the usual kind of
memory encoding which has a has two
consequences I mean one consequence is
that one doesn't remember exactly what
happened
uh and that's true of much of ordinary
life as well
but uh another consequence is it allows
experience without a whole lot of
processing
and
we're we're typically doing a tremendous
amount of processing thinking about the
information that we're getting uh
thinking not necessarily consciously but
uh we're doing a lot with the
information that we're getting and uh
using it to plan ahead to uh adjust the
overall structure of our network of
expectations about the world
and if you turn that off of I think you
get to see more in a sense of what's
going on because uh one isn't having to
expend the energy to do all of the
processing that we're constantly doing
so we don't this this also applies I
think in at least some sense to the
dream stage which is also an alternate
state of consciousness
one doesn't have to spend a lot of
effort for example
trying to figure out whether the object
you're seeing now is the same object
that you were saying a little while ago
oh so it's okay
if
that object is changing its
its properties in some uh interesting
way
so I think these experiences are very
interesting uh it it is kind of clear
why in a sense they're uh liberating or
can achieve a certain level of of house
cleaning in the mind
by
stripping away
expectations and not doing the kinds of
uh cognitive work that we're often doing
to cut experience up into little
manageable fragments
because all of that depends on being
able to keep a lot in memory
and to
devote a whole lot of energy to
computation so backing off from that uh
seems like clearly something that can be
valuable
say that again Chris
I said you're probably more familiar
with these sorts of experiences
uh in terms of their neurological and
also phenomenological properties
absolutely to be clear Chris does not
mean that I take lots of drugs it's
because I'm a psychiatrist
[Laughter]
um
so again that's a great question Ivy
you're going to be very cross with me
because I've got so much to say about
that question because I'll say it very
very quickly
um so
there is a very well worked out
literature addressing exactly this
question uh and some of the words that
Chris used in answer
um figure very prominently in this
literature and the literature has two
sides and I'll just start with the
notion of
um house cleaning and housekeeping and
the important insights one gets from
sleep Research into our constructive
realities and how sensitively they did
upon
um the Precision of our belief updating
so in the brain the Precision of relief
updating is literally described
um in predictive coding formulations of
this kind of information processing in
terms of precision weighted prediction
errors and the Precision is usually set
physiologically by neuromodulatory
transmitter systems things like 5H
serotonin 5-ht noradrenaline dopamine
oxytocin amino-like and and the key
inside here is that dreaming as an
altered state of consciousness is
principally determined by the status and
discharges of these ascending
neuromodulated transmitter systems so
there's a a very concrete very well
understood empirically set of mechanisms
that tie together the Precision of your
belief updating and the
um the differences in the way that we
make sense of our world even when asleep
you know when we are dreaming we are
still making sense of a world it's
actually our self-constructed world that
is sequestered from the actual sensory
input by turning down the Precision of
the sensory prediction error parents but
not reducing the Precision of all the
hierarchically deployed prediction
errors in our brain
um so dreaming and just the existence of
dreams I think is is as my
um as well colleague who died a few
years ago and Hobson one of the world's
experts on sleep and dreaming would say
if you want evidence for the brain as a
constructive organ making sense of its
sensory Impressions on its holographic
screen or its Markov blanket you need to
look no further than the fact that we
can dream that is the only reality we
really need to uh to worry about but it
does depend you know the the kind of
sense making does depend very very
um sensitively on neuromodulation
um and um
that controls the Precision just one
little link here because Chris also used
the word temperature in my world
Precision is inverse temperature
um so you talk about soft matte premises
in those temperature parameters that is
precision so we're talking about
cool-headed sense making
um now how does that relate to the other
literature well the other literature is
on waitful sense making where you
interfere with exactly the same
neurotransmitted systems so all
psychedelics
um
effectively act as agonists of private
to 2A receptors which are really
important receptor that's set in the
Precision or the gain or the Precision
weighting of the prediction errors and
that to a certain extent can be thought
of as the inverse of sleeping so here
you're emphasizing the Precision of
lower level sensory prediction errors
with respect to your higher deeper kinds
of constructs so I think
um the question was absolutely right
that that you know by pharmacologically
altering the Precision of our belief
updating on the temperature
differentially at different hierarchy
levels of deep sense making can have
profound effects on the way that we
exert control or put prior constraints
or pry beliefs in our experience into
the mix when making sense of our
Sensations I was just going to conclude
by um pointing to the literature on
psychedelics um the key or one of the
key authors in this field is a gentleman
old Robin Carhart Ares and the bottom
line of the story that he tells is that
psychedelics reduce the Precision of
very deep prior beliefs and enhance the
Precision of more sensory level
processing and that basically means that
you are dissolving or relaxing the
Precision of higher level higher level
beliefs so you are becoming more
attentive to the sensorium are we going
to quickly go to re yeah so uh the thing
so it's kind of a follow-up question to
what prakash asks then it is like you
know if there is a sense of Observer not
being there then how can how can that be
you know experience be valid or the
Consciousness be valid on that and of
and the reason why I say that it is a
follow-up question because uh because
the moment you we don't that's what Kyle
said just now we don't have that
distinction of you know observable is
observed and we don't go into that
distinction as much and then just factor
in of conceivability with the concept of
Markov blanket as how much that
conceivability can exist and beyond that
if there is what Kyle is referring as
Dark Void so if if it is audible uh you
can you guys can you know as prakash is
giving thumbs up yeah you can you guys
can you know answer on that I'll try to
say something here uh I I see this
question as asking about
the limit of weak interaction between
two systems so if you think about
a boundary between two systems that's
supporting some interaction one can
always think of that as a Communication
channel from a formal perspective and
someone can ask about the limit as the
bandwidth that that channel goes to zero
uh and as the bandwidth of the channel
goes to zero
there's no information exchange so there
is in a sense of no experiential content
anymore and I suspect that these
experiences oh that you're describing
are experiences of uh approaching that
limit of no information exchange across
the boundary I mean one one can
there's a kind of Brute Force way to
approach this limit is something like uh
using sensory deprivation
but of course that doesn't approach it
very closely because it doesn't remove
uh interception so I think uh I think
it's a it's a very difficult limit to
actually approach and and remain alive
um but I think one can get closer than
sensory deprivation yeah see you can
also argue that um certain sleep States
approach that in terms of neurochemical
sensory deprivation basically switching
off apart from
um afference from the ocular motor
system which are part of the central
nervous system everything else is
basically switched off so you
um you met one may be asking now well
okay if there's no information traffic
across my uh Markov blanket
um how do I make sense and I think the
the answer to that comes again
um from these this notion of a deeply
structured internal uh model that of
course is defined by a whole series of
Markov blankets inside the head so it
comes back to observing The Observer
um that there's still good information
processing you can do even the absence
of Sensations from the sensory receptors
that you know people have
um and there's an interesting
mathematical take on this which comes
back to business notion of housekeeping
um if you remember right at the
beginning we were talking about the
imperatives for or natural descriptions
of things that exist inside and with
Markov blankets
which is to maximize the
um evidence for effectively their
internal models evidence can always be
written down as accuracy minus
complexity which means there is still
evidence maximizing information
processing that can occur in the absence
of sensory inputs which can minimize the
complexity and what that translates to
in sleep is basically exactly the the
housekeeping removing redundant parts of
the structure as we rehearse and find
out what associations that we built up
during the day are no longer necessary
to provide a simple minimally complex
but accurate account of what we have
seen to date but this only works because
I you know there are Markov blankets
within Markov blankets screens within
screens within screen so it will only
work with
um deep generative models a thermostat
will not be able to Dream Will you and I
can
so uh but just just connect it to the
previous question as well
um I'm I don't know anything about
um
that you're the Buddhist um constructs
that would be useful to yeah to um to
complement this perspective but it does
strike me that
um the action of psychedelics
um is in many senses trying to Aspire to
states of mindfulness
which you know where if you're a skilled
meditator that basically means you now
have some volitional control over the
attention of the Precision that you
afford certain sensory Sensations say
it's by breathing or you know another
kind of modality which of course is
exactly switching off the Precision of
the deeper higher internal uh structures
which would be in one sense
um
um a dissolution of selfhood
um that is the you know the um red as
having higher beliefs and constraints in
the game when making sense of your
Sensations that would be if you like the
aspirational target of ultimate kinds of
mindfulness so I think there is a deep
connection you know between the role of
psychedelics and pharmacologically
biasing your sense making to very
precise low-level sensory inputs
um and the same ambition of mindful
states that are you know that are the
Holy Grail of certain kinds kinds of
meditation the final point I want to
make in relation to
um
or through the lens of Psychiatry is
that there are some very interesting
out-of-body experiences and
derealization depersonalization
experiences that people have that can be
accessed through the use of psychedelics
and one of them is the sense that I am
not me or I am not even a person
um and this kind of depersonalization
can be truly awful if your subject to it
um and what it tells you is that the
hypothesis I am me
is just another construct
and then it doesn't necessarily always
have to be in play when you're making
sense of your Sensations and we'd sort
of take it for granted
um that we it's me sensing and having
these experiences but that's just part
of the self model and it is just a model
it's just a hypothesis that we use to
make sense of things and there's no
reason why you can't explore alternative
hypotheses that I am not me and
sometimes if you commit to that and that
provides great it is a better
explanation for these very precise
prediction errors that may be
pharmacologically or pathologically
um precise
um then you will experience
um a kind of nihilism of a deeply
disturbing sort where you no longer
sense that you are you and there are all
sorts of interesting symptoms like
Capgras symptoms where that same kind of
um identification
um is transplanted to other people so my
wife no longer is actually my wife she
becomes an imposter
um so a lot of things we take for
granted in terms of selfhood and
self-awareness can be very very fragile
in
um some psychiatric conditions or under
some uh under some uh under some under
some drugs but you know I don't know
whether that's the kind of Buddhist
perspective of the question that was uh
was chasing just for your benefit
absolutely in chapter 27 of the diamond
Sutra it uh warrants against nihilism
just for this exact uh point that you
brought up uh so intuitively so thank
you
thank you we've got to move on now we
have only seven more minutes uh we're
gonna move on to John and then maroon
and then that was it it's going to be
end of it because we only got seven more
minutes
well thanks Ivy I I'll make this uh
relatively brief I I'm thinking of
telling my wife that she's an imposter
so that I don't so she doesn't whisk me
off to the desert as
um at any rate this has been great I'm
kind of a I'm a novice physicist in all
this I'm only exploited by ivy for my my
audio engineering skills which I have so
on display today but I wanted to just I
have lots of questions but I just want
to one that's occurred to me over and
over and it's been something that's been
nagging at me for some time is this idea
you know I people talk about the hard
conscious of hard problem of
Consciousness uh qualia and all of that
but it seems to me that the harder
problem really is about curiosity what
you guys were talking about curiosity I
use I always use the word creativity I
try to imagine for me artificial
intelligence will really be artificial
intelligence if and only if it gets to
the point where it can look out at the
stars and say wow what is that
um maybe we could design a rocket ship
and put things on it to go out there and
take a look uh you know or collect
samples and bring them back and I that
strikes me as a really hard barrier
creativity and it's lesser versions of
that perhaps are in the Arts and
everything else but anything having to
do with creativity strikes me as the
really hard problem of Consciousness and
I wonder if you think artificial
intelligence will actually get us to
something will artificial intelligence
be that good at any point is that even
possible
stump them
I I was going to suggest that that you
could start with uh
all right yes yeah it does strike me as
a question probably more for Carl
especially since that's what he's
supposed to be doing right no absolutely
I think what you've just said is
absolutely spot on
um and I I think that um the Next
Generation
Um of artificial intelligence you know
it's probably closer than you might
think and it does exactly rest upon this
curiosity so when Siri starts asking you
questions as opposed to you asking it
questions then we'll know we're getting
much much closer so I think you've
identified exactly the next moment you
know the next gtp3 GTP uh moment it's
going to be when these schemes are not
just generating content for us that
actually want to know about us and how
the world works and then start asking
questions that has this that has this um
aspect of curiosity this response to
epistemic affordance is that you are
absolutely right you know
um is one expression of creativity and
I'm just mindful of uh one of my friends
Jurgen Smith who the inventor of the
long short term memory STM that is in
your mobile phones probably at the very
moment he's always
um played um a or told a story which um
produces a very close link between the
um that complexity minimization that
evidence maximization or free energy
minimization that we were talking about
before which when read in terms of
information Series right is called
compression so the key role of
compression in terms of getting simple
but accurate accounts as simple as
possible no simpler accounts of our
sensorium but that manifests in terms of
behavior and actively going out there
and doing smart data mining it manifests
as curiosity it manifests literally in
his word as artificial thumb so we come
back to what Chris was saying before
about playing play is itself
um one expression of this uncertainty
reducing imperative yo whether it's
children playing together or you
playfully asking me with ridiculous
questions or whether
um
it is you know the kind of play
um the kind of curiosity
um that um
so yes I've witted on for two for too
long but to my mind fun creative
creativity and curiosity
um are are all expresses of exactly the
next thing that we'd expect to see from
our intelligent artifacts very good
Moran yeah um thank you very much uh to
both of our guests um as well as the
panel members
um I just had a I have a few questions
but I'm just going to narrow it down to
one and it is about one of the
statements that was mentioned uh to be
an observer is to exist I would have
thought that to be in order to be an
observer at the very least you have to
exist right so because for example a
book exists right but and because it
exists you can think about a Markov
blanket around it but again having said
that there is a Markov blanket around it
like if you want to say that it's
observing because it exists then you can
think about like I don't know like
imagine a sense serious State and an
action state but because it doesn't have
cell food it can be the sensory set
would be to be read to be thrown around
for example in the past in a completely
passive sense and the action state of a
book that doesn't have cell food could
be palpating my my eyeballs so that I
could like read it like you know like it
it's not as a certain state of like a
weird sort of action selection mechanism
so just want to hear your thoughts um
like if there's time both Professor
first and then Professor feels that
would it make sense to say that in order
to be Observer at the very least you
have to exist and plus other conditions
thank you
yeah if I could start I
I think that's very fair I I think the
point that Carl was making with that
slogan uh and a point with which I agree
is that if something exists
in the sense of
it it has a stable and weak interaction
with its environment
so so if if we are outside Observers we
can see that thing and say oh that's an
object that's a thing that's stable in
time that has persistence
if a thing is stable in time and it
persists
then it is interacting with its
environment
and that interaction is two-way
um and it's interact the interaction we
may regard it just as thermal
right we we may just see it as heat
exchange
but it's still an interaction
and so this very minimal sense of
observation that we've been discussing
is just interaction it's just physical
interaction by systems that are the
systems that have a sufficiently stable
boundary
go ahead
hello
no I was just going to say that's that's
that's what we mean by this slogan that
existence is interaction interaction is
observation
uh just to reinforce that point
um and also celebrate the the notion of
a book I've never been asked that before
that's an excellent an excellent example
usually people ask about Stones
Chris's observation that the stone is
actually observing the temperature of
the ambient environment thank you very
much and this is a very Elemental basil
kind of observation and which is you
know that's not the kind of observation
we're obsession with curious breached
with these deep splotches but it's still
observation from the point of view
um from one point of view but the book
is is even more interesting because
because it has a language in it it is
actually observing human culture of the
human race
so very much like desire paths in Niche
construction
things that basically exist and can be
read as the environment learning about
its inhabitants behind the environments
Markov blanket you can actually read the
printing of the book and the fact it was
made by human beings but also the
content in the form of the book in and
of itself as one way of observing its
environment but probably best read as
learning about its existence is it it
owes its existence due to the printed
word
so it is learning about you now I know
it's not observation in the moment but
at a certain time scale it's a kind of
observation
thank you thank you very much
won't ask you any questions so it's you
don't have to worry about it
I think we wind down to the
internet or both of your time so can we
all give a massive thank you to
Professor fiston with us today and Dr
Phil today please everyone
yeah it's not expensive yes
and thanks to you all for for
interesting questions
happy Lunar New Year
thank you for your interesting answer
thank you yeah good thank you
in conversation thank you so much for
both great mornings thank you hope to
see you guys
thank you very much
ciao
thank you for organizing this question
a really profound discussion in the
question and the session which I think
if anybody is interested should listen
to the replay a few times because
they've been very deep into the
architecture
what Consciousness is
put in words it's not put in words in
books this came out exactly through an
exchange of conversations and this is
what this kind of discussion yes just to
be cleared for people in the clubhouse
room we are still sitting here and and
uh both Dr friston in fields are are
listening in
so you know if you want to like sneak in
some uh you know nice comments that
would be great too but I think we are
going to wind down the zoom meeting
because because I have to go sorry you
guys
thank you very much
[Music]